Good evening, everyone.
大家晚安，我們擔誤了一點時間
We'll start now.
所以我們馬上開始
Welcome you all here today and thank you for attending our presentation.
非常歡迎大家來參加今天的活動
This topic for tonight is introducing two development boards
今天我們活動的主題是介紹兩個開發板
The first one is LinkIt Smart 7688
第一個叫LinkIt Smart 7688
It's very popular among the communities now
最近非常的紅，在社群上很多朋友在玩它
Our speakers today are all masters
今天我們請來的講者都是大神級的
The first is a senior engineer from SeeedStudio -- Yihui
第一個是SeeedStudio的資深工程師 -- Yihui
He is involved in projects like 7688, RePhone, and Wio Link,
Yihui參與7688還有RePhone還有Wio Link
and many others.
和滿多其它項目的開發
The second is a front end engineer from MediaTek -- Blue, Bo-Ju Chen
然後第二個是聯發科的前端工程師 -- Blue 陳柏儒
Everyone knows him, so I'll skip the intro.
大家都認識他了，所以就不用介紹了
and the third, Sam. The one who is installing a rice cooker.
然後第三個 -- Sam，現在正在裝鍋子的大神
Last week he entered 2015 Mobile Hero Contest and got 2nd place.
上禮拜參加Mobile Hero通訊大賽，拿到亞軍
His demo will come with a SeeedStudio product,
今天demo的是用SeeedStudio的產品
called RePhone. It's a Smart Rice Cooker.
叫RePhone，做的智能電子鍋
and, his partner, (Casear)
然後，他的同伴 (Casear)
a master in full stack development.
則是full stack的高手
Then the team Makee will show you
然後Makee團隊待會會跟大家介紹
How to write Python and do I/O control in 7688.
怎麼用7688去寫Python，跟做一些控制
They made a FPV 4WD remote control car with a 7688.
他們用7688做了實境的四驅車
The video is on Youtube.
影片在Youtube上都有
and last, this is me (Jollen).
然後最後是我 (Jollen)
For today's agenda,
那今天的議程安排
I'll start first,
待會我會先開場
with OpenWRT, around half an hour.
大概講半小時OpenWRT
Then Yihui, Blue, Sam, Team Makee
然後再來我們就請Yihui、Blue，還有Sam、Makee團隊
.
跟大家介紹
I'll start the first agenda item.
所以我就開場
Before the topic,
在演講之前
I'll show you something within a minute.
我很快用一分鐘demo一個東西
This is a new dev board bring to here by Yihui.
這個是Yihui今天才剛帶過來，熱騰騰的開發版
Wio Link.
Wio Link
This should be its debut in Taiwan
應該是第一次在台灣現身
This afternoon, in a coffee shop, with his help,
下午我就跟他在一家咖啡店，請他幫忙
the firmware was replaced
我把它的firmware換掉
with NodeMCU.
換成NodeMCU的firmware
and quickly wrote a program to take photo.
然後很快寫了一隻小程式，可以用來拍照
On the desk over there,
那在旁邊的桌子上
it's a GoPro.
我放了一個GoPro
Here's a button,
這裡有個按鈕
It was pressed, you may heard the GoPro taking a picture.
按下去，大家應該會聽到GoPro拍照的聲音
Just took me half an hour
大概半個小時就做完了
to made a product like this.
可以打造這種產品
Of course, either Wio Link or 7688 will do.
當然用Wio Link也可以，用7688也可以
It's simple behind the scenes.
原理很簡單
Because there's a web server inside GoPro.
因為在GoPro裡面其實藏了一個web server
Just hack it, and you'll know the REST API.
你只要去hack它，就知道它的REST API是什麼
Then we could use either 7688 or Wio Link,
我們就用7688或是Wio Link
to call the API.
去call API就可以了
Configure it into AP mode and connect to it,
開機的時候可以設成AP模式之後連上它
the web server could be called.
call他的web server API
It's a lot of fun.
所以，其實是非常好玩的
In the next coming up presentation by Yihui,
等一下Yihui的演講裡面
He'll mention a new concept
也會跟大家稍微提一個滿新的概念
called WoT.
叫做WoT
This presentation will introduce
今天很快跟各位用一些時間
OpenWRT and its packages within 7688.
介紹一下7688裡面OpenWRT的套件
A quick rundown of
我會很快的run down一下
downloading source code, compiling firmware,
從下載source code、編譯firmware
installing extra kernel module,
可能裡面有需要新增一些kernel module
or say driver.
一些驅動程式
and installing extra packages.
有一些額外的套件
.
把整個過程大概rundown一下
Lots of them are already scattered around the web
網路上其實都找得到文件
I'll organize them and put on GitHub. https://github.com/jollen/7688-embedded-linux
我今天會再整理一次，放在我的GitHub上
It should a time saver for you.
相信今天這樣的整理，應該會幫助大家節省時間
.
減少搜尋文件的時間
I'll present 4 important topics of 7688.
今天大概講四個7688比較重要的主題
The first is the embedded Linux distro,
第一個是它用的embedded Linux的發佈版本
OpenWRT.
叫做OpenWRT
Its history,
OpenWRT的歷史沿革
origin, and usage.
還有它的起源跟用途
The next coming up by Yihui will have this, too.
待會Yihui也會幫大家做介紹
The second topic, installing a USB network interface
然後可能需要在7688上面
in 7688.
安裝一個USB網卡
Because with 7688 in AP mode,
因為7688，你把它當作AP在用的時候
it needs another network interface to access LAN.
它還是需要一個網路對外
We could go Guang Hua Computer Market and buy a cheap
我們可以去光華商場買到那種很便宜的
WiFi USB stick with a Realtek chip,
Realtek的WiFi USB stick
and connect it to 7688.
把它接在7688上
Then you need to install Realtek drivers to make it work.
這個時候你就需要Realtek的相關驅動程式
It doesn't come with default config.
這些default都沒有
You need to tick the checkbox and compile.
你可去把它打勾以及編譯
I'll go through it.
我等一下會很快rundown一下這個過程
The third topic, inside the firmware,
再來編好的firmware裡面
it's a small footprint filesystem.
其實是一個小型的root filesystem
contains packages such as BusyBox,
包含像BusyBox這樣的套件
which includes many utilities,
這個套件裡面有很多工具
and extra applications
也有額外的一些application
Today I'll use a simple topic called ffmpeg
今天我用一個比較簡單的題目，叫做ffmpeg
Because the firmware of 7688 does not include ffmpeg by default.
因為7688的firmware，default沒有ffmpeg
If I want to connect a web cam to it,
可是我想在上面接一個web cam
then use ffmpeg to do straming,
然後用ffmpeg去做串流
HTTP live streaming.
做HTTP的live streaming
I'll show you how to compile it.
怎麼去編譯，等一下也會很快的rundown一下
And, inside the root filesystem,
然後，root filesystem裡面
There are some important services,
有一些很重要的service daemon
like mDNS.
像mDNS
I'll make a briefing so that you could study further.
很快介紹一下、幫大家起個頭
Basically, it's a embbed Linux distro,
基本上，它是一個embedded Linux的發佈套件
which was derived from Open Embedded project.
最早最早，其實是Open Embedded專案開始
.
然後衍生出來的
Open Embedded is a "build system"
Open Embedded是一個編譯系統
My first experience with it, was its predecessor,
我最早接觸它的前身，OpenWRT的前身
long long ago, nearly 10 years,
是古老之前，將近十年前
oh, more than 10 years.
已經十年前了
There's a open source project, OpenMoko.
台灣有一個開放源碼的專案，叫OpenMoko
I used such a build system from that time.
從那時候開始用這樣的編譯系統
Inside OpenWRT,
OpenWRT裡面
includes many utilities and commands.
基本就是一些常用的工具跟指令
util-linux
util-linux
uClibc, the standard C library, everyone knows it.
uClibc，這是標準C程式庫，大家都曉得
BusyBox, the familiar package.
BusyBox，這個也是耳熟能詳的發佈套件
It contains lots of utilities.
裡面有很多工具指令
If you don't see a particular command inside,
你可能有一些常用的Linux command、或utilities
just go to the config menu and tick the checkbox.
沒有的話，就進去它的選單打勾就好了
and last, OpenWRT has a buildin web interface,
最後，OpenWRT裡內建web管理介面
everyone already seen it,
這個大家應該都看過
so I'll skip it.
今天就不特別介紹
The first thing, prepare an Ubuntu host,
第一件事情，要準備一台Ubuntu電腦
the install necessary packages.
然後把缺乏的套件補上
this, unzip, is a required package,
這個，unzip是必要的
It's not listed in the 7688 official document on GitHub.
這個在7688官方的GitHub文件，少列了這個
Then you clone the OpenWRT source code.
再來是要把OpenWRT的source code，clone下來
It looks like this after cloning.
clone下來後，就長這樣子
all things are packed as distribution,
所有的東西，他都打包成distribution
it's convenient.
就是發佈套件，其實還滿方便的
For checkout, use the 15.05 release branch.
check out的話，可以用15.05的版本
It's mentioned in the 7688 official document on GitHub.
這是在7688官方GitHub上文件上講的
This is the newest master branch,
這是最新的master
but usually you'll get into trouble with it. (laugh)
通常編譯都會有問題，不會成功 (笑)
Feeds, customized packages.
feeds，就是客製化的套件
That's the meaning of feeds in OpenWRT.
OpenWRT的feeds意思是這樣
MediaTek Labs provides feeds for 7688.
聯發科，MediaTek Labs有提供7688的feeds
You need to add the feeds into this config file.
所以你要把他的feeds，加到這個設定檔
That's the official 7688 packages.
這是7688官方提供的套件
The last 2 commands are self-describing.
最後二個指令就不用講了
Then, give the command...
最後，要先下一個叫做...
(make prereq)
(make prereq)
to check the prerequisite.
去檢查一些必要的東西
then, go to the config menu (make menuconfig)
再來，進到選單 (make menuconfig)
"make prereq" is needed for first time only.
make prereq只有在第一次才需要執行
The first time you cloned OpenWRT source code.
把OpenWRT下載之後，去用它的第一次
After that, you just use menuconfig every time.
之後都直接進menuconfig就可以了
This menu, integrates BusyBox, kernel config,
這個選單，整合了BusyBox、kernel config
lots of configurations.
東西很多
Browse among them,
有空就慢慢看
you'll get an idea of what's included.
就會知道裡面幫大家打包了哪一些套件
According to the Internet, more than 2000 packages.
根據網路上的說明，有超過2000個套件
Versatile.
應有盡有
According to MediaTek Labs, make correct choices.
聯發科說要把這些選項，勾選正確
The first one, Target System -- Ralink.
第一個是Target System -- Ralink
Then MT7688 based boards.
再來是MT7688 based boards
Next, Profile.
下一個，Profile
It goes without saying.
看就知道
Next, compile.
然後下編譯指令
Exit, remember to Save.
離開，然後記得存檔
It won't ask for saving because I didn't make changes.
因為我沒有變更，沒有問我要不要儲存
This will give more verbose messages (make V=99)
這樣的畫面會比較多 (make V=99)
.
就是我們講的，冗長(?)
looks like a mess
一大堆亂七八糟的訊息
just remove it (V=99) and you'll get out of the these.
如果你不想看的話，也不用加
My server has 4 cores
像我的server是四核心
I'll enable Amazon instances during compilation of large distros.
編譯比較大包的distribution的時候，我會去開Amazon的instance
enable 4- or 8-core instance
去開四核、不然就八核心的instance
and disable it when done. Because it's charged by time.
編完之後再關掉，很為很貴啊，要算時間的
it has 4 cores, compile with 8 threads.
這個是四核心，可以用八個線程去編譯
-j, followed by the number of CPUs*2. It's a well-known skill.
-j, 後面是CPU數量乘以二，這是慣例
Finally, the finished firmware will be here.
最後，編好的fimrware檔在這裡
Just wait for it to finish.
我們等它一下
I used 7688 these weeks, and an idea came into my mind
我這幾個禮拜試用7688，有一個感覺
For studying embedded Linux,
假設要以embedded Linux當做學習主題的話
students are really blissful these days.
現在學embedded Linux的工程師，真的是好幸福
The study days at several years ago was painful.
不像以前，用的開發板很痛苦
I won't go through the detail of the pain.
為什麼會很痛苦就不講了
Ignorance is bliss.
不知道的才是幸福
For example, it will took several cups of coffee
比如說光是download Linux就要花好多杯咖啡的時間
to just download Linux source code, around 4 cups.
一次喝掉四杯
even more, compilation errors, totally hopeless...
然後發現它又錯誤，都很想哭
then went back to compiling again.
再回去重新編譯
and no such a convenient distro like OpenWRT,
也沒有像OpenWRT這麼方便的發佈套件
sometimes you need to start from source code, run configure,
甚至有時候你要從source code解壓，然後執行configure
from the basic command.
這個指令開始
I see several friends nodding
我看有幾個朋友點頭
we are from the same generation
應該我們是同一個世代
It's really bliss these days.
現在真的是滿幸福
Actually, we could consider it as a small Linux PC
對，其實可以把它當做一台小的Linux PC
learning Linux programming
可以在裡面學習怎麼寫Linux的programming
Take it to school, it's a really good choice as a study platform.
拿到學校去當教學平台，其實滿不錯的
After compiling is finished, like the handout said,
編譯好之後呢，就像講義講的
You could find it in this place.
可以在一個地方找到最後的firmware
Then perform the firmware update procedure.
然後就把它更新就好
There 2 ways to do so
更新的方法有二個
One is by USB, there's a video on YouTube
一個用USB，YouTube上有一篇
That's Macpaul, over there, produced by him.
那是我們的Macpaul大大，在這邊，他製作的影片
Or use the Web UI
不然就是用它的web介面也可以
If both do not work well, just ask Bo-Ju Chen, he's there.
再不行，去問陳柏儒就好了，他在旁邊
I was work with something new this week.
我這禮拜在做一個東西
Connect a web cam to 7688, and do live streaming
就是想用7688接web cam，做視訊串流
But my architecture for streaming
不過我的視訊串流的架構
is slightly different from others
跟一般網路上看到的，有點不一樣
the stream will be pushed to another server
我是想先把視訊推送到一台server
then the server push the stream the all users
server再推送給所有的user
instead of pushing by 7688
而不是由7688直接推送給所有的user
push by server-class hardware
是用server等級的
Because the push action will be processed on time
因為這樣處理才會來得及
and 7688 won't get overloaded.
7688也才不會那麼忙錄
Anyway, I need HLS,
Anyway，我需要用HLS
HTTP Live Streaming.
HTTP的live streaming
The streaming technology by Apple.
這是Apple的串流技術
push the stream to a server.
把它推送到server上
The easiest way is to run ffmpeg with just a command.
最容易的方法，就是用ffmpeg去下一個command
but the the firmware doesn't come with it.
然後裡面沒有
It doesn't matter, just went to menuconfig, make a tick
沒有也不礙事，就進到menuconfig，然後打勾
check it as M, modularize, that's easy.
把它勾選成M，就是modularize就可以了
Because only a new package was compiled,
因為只需要多編譯出一個套件
so no need to update the whole firmware.
所以不需要整個firmware更新
download it to the dev board, then opkg install it.
就download到板子上，然後用opkg去install就可以了
check it
就把他打勾
some dependent packages are required, such as ffmpeg library
它有一些相依套件，比如說ffmpeg的library
so we need to download 2 package files,
所以等一下，其實必需要把二個套件
the first, libffmpeg
第一個叫libffmpeg
the second, ffmpeg
第二個就是ffmpeg套件，總共二個
to the dev board.
必須把它download到開發板上面
The most frequently used command during Linux programming,
學Linux程式設計，最常用的command line
are probably find and grep.
大概就是find跟grep
Copy the package files of ffmpeg and its library
把ffmpeg還有它的library，這二個檔案
to the dev board via network, then install them.
透過網路把它copy到板子去安裝就好了
scp them to the dev board, then install
把它scp進去、install就可以了
No need to update the whole firmware.
不需要整個firmware重新安裝
A step further, you could make your own feeds.
更進一步，你也可以製作自己的feeds
Please refer to OpenWRT manual,
請參考OpenWRT的手冊
to add more packages, lots of packages here.
去加套件、加一些指令，這麼多東西
So actually, 7688 itself is not the most important.
所以，其實7688不是那麼重要
In embedded Linux, the knowledge of system admin,
embedded Linux，就是Linux系統管理面的一些知識
is rather the point.
反倒是重點
Getting around in Linux before,
只不過說以前玩Linux
you need a big PC or a server, somewhat inconvenient.
可能一台PC、一台server，太麻煩了
Now we have this, a Linux machine that fits in your pocket.
現在有個東西，放在口袋就可以當Linux PC了
So 7688 is indeed a nice gadget.
所以7688確實是個好東西
Also, support our own products.
另外就是我們要支持國貨，不要去用別人做的
.
好!
Just mentioned, scp package files to the dev board,
這剛才講的，把它scp到板子上之後
install them with opkg.
就用opkg，去把它install起來就好了
I'll skip it.
這邊我就不demo
Next, kernel module, this is also
再來，kernel module，這個也是滿常見的
a common issue
滿常見的issue
Connect a spare USB WiFi adapter to 7688.
家裡有不要用的USB網卡，接到7688
All of mine have Realtek chip inside, I don't know why.
我家的都是Realtek的，不知道為什麼
Why they are all Realtek?
怎麼都是Realtek
Maybe they are cheap, in my guess.
可能比較便宜吧，我在猜
Then you could come to the list of kernel modules
然後你們就可以從kernel modules這裡面
and find out...
去找到...
relevant options,
相關的一些選項
or devices drivers,
或是device drives的選項
802.11 libraries,
802.11的library
and associated stack.
跟它的stack
This is the driver for my spare Realtek 8188...
這是在我家撿到的Realtek 8188的...
Oh, no EU, another one.
咦，不是EU，是另外一個
USB wireless stck with 818x chip
818x的USB wireless stick
The same steps, compile it,
那一樣把它編譯
then copy the kernel modules to dev board.
編譯完把kernel module copy到板子就好
(find ./ -name "*.ko" -print)
(find ./ -name "*.ko" -print)
My lazy way of copying,
我比較偷懶，就會把它整個modules目錄全部打包
is to create a tarball and copy it, extract it.
把它的tarball，就是壓縮包，copy到板子上，再去解壓
So I don't need to copy them individually,
就不要一個一個copy
How do you know the location of the compiled binaries?
怎麼知道編出來的東西放在哪邊呢?
Just use the command frequency top 1, find.
就是使用率排行榜第一名的指令，叫find
Drivers.
驅動程式
The above are steps about adding packages, and adding device drivers.
大概就是額外的套件、然後額外的驅動程式
First one is connecting a USB WiFi dongle to 7688,
我就把7688接了一個USB網卡
so it could connect to the Internet.
讓它可以連到Internet
Because the on-board WiFi will be used as a Access Point,
因為它上面的WiFi，我要當做AP來用
to connect with my cellphone or computer.
去接手機或接我的電腦
It needs 2 WiFi connection.
這需要二個WiFi
Another one is USB web cam.
另外就是USB的web cam
Use the camera with ffmpeg to do live streaming,
我要用ffmpeg做streaming
As a result, I have a small home surveillance camera.
這樣就有一個小型的家用視訊監控器
After streaming to a server,
那streaming到server上之後
of course you could watch the video on a web page or mobile app.
當然你可以在網頁或手機app去看到它
But I'll skip it.
這個部份，今天就不另外做介紹
Adding kernel modules, how to compile and install.
額外的kernel module怎麼編譯、怎麼安裝
Ok! After boot, you'll find many daemons in the 7688.
好！開機之後，你會發現7688裡面有很多service daemon
If today we are in a class in the school,
照理說，如果今天是在學校上課
The teacher will introduce them one by one, very detailed.
老師要一個一個講
It needs a lot of patience,
像這種就要很有耐心
to understand thoroughly.
才能夠把技術學到很透徹
So you could buy a book such as... Ubuntu Linux system admin, and study with it.
應該比如買一本... Ubuntu Linux系統管理的書，回家 K
or books for LPIC certification,
或是去買LPIC認證考試的書
That's a well-organized material.
那個整理的比較好
Buy LPIC 101, 102 and study.
去買101、102這二本，回來K
It will told us,
因為它會告訴我們
the utilities and config files for system admin,
系統管理的工具跟設定檔是什麼
Although for some utilities, the config files will have a different path and content
不過有些工具的設定檔的路徑跟內容
compared to OpenWRT.
跟OpenWRT又不太一樣
But it doesn't matter,
那倒是沒有差別
you could adapter yourselves to the new environment.
這些細節，我們都可以隨機應變的
But, the first,
只是說，第一個
avahi? Why does it so "high"? (laugh)
這個什麼avahi? 不知道在high什麼 (笑)
avahi... what's that?
avahi... 到底是什麼東西呢?
It also appeared in Ubuntu.
這個Ubuntu就有了
It's...
這個是...
mDNS service.
mDNS的服務
I'll use it later, so just take a quick introduction.
我稍後有用它，所以給他很快講解一個東西
We have a limited time frame today,
因為今天時間比較少
In coming up sessions,
等一下...
Pay your attention to the speech, don't practice by yourself.
每一個大神在演講的時候，就不要跟著操作
It's dangerous to practice,
因為這太冒險了
because you may not be able to catch up. Leave the practice after the end.
聽都來不及聽，就回去再練習就好了
I'll pick up some important diagrams,
我等一下會以節錄圖的方式來講解
to save your time.
節省一些時間
There are web server, samba, everybody knows them.
然後，裡面有web server、有samba，這個大家都曉得
and time sync, NTP time sync.
還有對時，NTP對時
and dropbear, the ssh server and client.
還有像dropbear，是ssh的server跟client
Those are what everyone familiar with.
大家比較常聽到的，是這幾個
After the 7688 boots, you could find this directory (/etc/avahi)
把7688開機之後，可以發現這個目錄 (/etc/avahi)
These are config files.
這是它的設定檔
and these are service groups.
這些都是service group
and... what's the function of mDNS service?
那... mDNS在做什麼的呢?
I'll demo with 7688.
不然我用7688板子來demo一下好了
mDNS is important for me,
mDNS對我來講很重要
because part of my job is giving demo for IoT products.
因為我是在做一些IoT的demo
I want to be able to do service discovery in LAN.
我想在區網裡面做服務的discover
To find out what's on the network.
去找找看有什麼東西
So mDNS, aka zero config, is important for me.
所以mDNS -- zero config，這樣的服務對我來講很重要
7688 could be discovered via mDNS,
甚至我可以透過mDNS去找到7688
then connect a temperature sensor to 7688 Duo.
然後用7688 Duo接溫度感測器
An inspiring idea.
會有什麼樣的火花出現呢?
Later Yihui will have an introduction for you.
等一下讓Yihui來跟大家介紹
My 7688 should now connected to the same AP... right.
然後，我的7688現在應該是連到同一個AP，沒有錯
My computer is a Mac,
我的電腦是Mac
There's a command...
可以在上面找到一個指令，叫做...
(dns-sd)
(dns-sd)
Let's go to the manual page, man page
我們去看一下manual page，看一下man
One of the arguments is like this...
其中有一個指令是這樣子
(dns-sd -B _http._tcp)
(dns-sd -B _http._tcp)
This is service name (LinkIt Smart7688...)
然後這個就是service name (LinkIt Smart7688...)
This is service type (_http._tcp)
這個是service type (_http._tcp)
So I find the type
所以我去找一下這個type
which provides the service
能夠提供這個服務的
(cd /etc/avahi/services)
(cd /etc/avahi/services)
(cat http.service)
(cat http.service)
It has lots of fun, really.
這個真是的很好玩
I never thought it before, a Linux PC,
以前從來沒有想過，一台Linux PC
a complete Linux command line environment,
這麼完整的Linux command line環境
Come with a small board which fits into the pocket.
可以有這麼小的板子放在口袋
Dev boards are used to be very large before.
以前大家的開發板都做的很大一張
When I was studying, I made it like a briefcase.
在唸書的時候，還把它做成行李箱
Somewhat exaggerated.
有點誇張
Now it's evolved into such a small size.
然後現在把它做到這麼小
It's very good for us.
真的還滿不錯的，很好用
This is one of the config files.
這是其中一個設定檔
On a Mac with mDNS,
所以我可以在Mac上，有mDNS的Mac上
I could find this service
找到這個服務
After the service was found, I could do this (dns-sd -R ...)
找到這個服務之後，我可以這樣子
Consult the document for these arguments.
這些指令讓大家自己查詢
What I want to emphasize,
其實我的意思，很簡單
during this phase,
到這個階段
It has nothing to do with 7688, embedded Linux, etc.
已經不關乎7688、或什麼embedded Linux，或什麼嵌入式系統的關題了
A more important background knowledge, is Linux administration.
而是涉及到一個更重要的基礎知識，叫Linux系統管理
This is what just mentioned (service group)
這是剛才講的 (service group)
a demo (service discover)
一個demo (service discover)
I'll commit the slides to GitHub.
等一下會把這一份slides，commit到我的GitHub上面
the name on GitHub is ... 7688-embedded-linux
GitHub上的名字叫做... 7688-embedded-linux
These are my slides,
這個是我的簡報
called index.html
簡報檔叫index.html
.
這一份就是
You can search for my name on GitHub first,
你們可以在GitHub先搜尋我的帳號
My name is Jollen.
我的名字叫Jollen
Go to GitHub and search for "jollen"
你們可以到GitHub去搜尋我的名字，叫jollen
You'll find the slides, 7688-embedded-linux.
應該可以滿容易找到這一份slides，7688-embedded-linux
It's not there now, I haven't commit it.
現在上去看不到，因為我還沒有commit上去
Just after the of the presentation.
等一下，或回家之後
Lastly, I'd like to share something,
最後，我想分享一個東西
not mentioned in the slides.
在我的slides沒有
It will appear in Yihui's slides.
但是待會Yihui的slides會有
Recently I want to use Wio Link,
我最近想用Wio Link
an ESP8266 dev board.
這個是ESP8266的開發板
This afternoon I spent sometime with it, it's really a good dev board,
下午玩了一下，我覺得它真的很棒
I think I won't use NodeMCU anymore,
所以我以後應該就不想用NodeMCU了
This afternoon,
下午用了一點時間
I replaced the Wio Link firmware with NodeMCU firmware.
把Wio Link的firmware換成NodeMCU的firmware
Because it's more convenient to use sensors,
因為它外接sensor比較方便
no need to connect daughterboards.
不用接shell board，子板
I want to make it a temperature-sensing device,
這個我想要回去，把它整個做成溫度感測裝置
put them everywhere in my home.
放在各個角落
the temperature data could be pushed via some protocol,
溫度的數據，可以透過某些協定
to a proxy,
即時推送到proxy
a "proxy" is what we called "gateway" before.
proxy就是以前我們講的gateway
7688 is a good choice as a gateway.
我想用7688做gateway，應該是滿不錯的一個選擇
the job of a gateway,
gateway的工作
is to collect various sensor data,
就是把家裡sensor的數據，集中起來之後
and push them to the cloud.
往雲端去送
It has such a small size, just what I need.
它這麼小，滿符合我的需求
Because I want to do something,
因為我想做一件事情
put it in to a socket.
把它埋到插座裡面
The wall socket in the home.
家裡的插座，把它埋進去
If possible, my friends in Shenzen who is doing hardware manufacturing business,
甚至可以的話，找我在深圳做硬體的朋友
could help me make it just like ordinary wall socket.
直接做成牆壁的插座就好
just like "Smart Sockets" in the marketplace which have build-in WiFi.
現在不是很多插座都有內置WiFi嗎
make it "embedded" inside the socket.
把它做成插座，可以embed到家裡的裝潢
so the dev board won't be exposed in the beautiful home decoration.
不然，板子那麼醜一個，在旁邊，怪怪的
Recently an idea came into my mind,
我突然最近有感而發
dev boards now could be treated as end products.
這種東西，其實可以把它當做成品來看待
.
product
Dev boards were considered semi-finished products,
以前的開發板，大家都當成半成品
After the development finished, laying out a new circuit board from the ground up,
板子玩一玩，然後重lay板子，把它做的很漂亮
then mechanism design, ID design,
還要畫機構，還要做ID設計
we could only buy them in the store after such a long procedure.
才能去商店把它買下來
So I feel that maker age is really lots of fun.
所以我覺得創客時代，真的很有趣
Recently there is a group buying,
最近剛好有團購
I bought lots of boards,
團購了很多，自己也留了很多
with my spare time such as New Year, Christmas to play around with them,
自己留起來，想說用過年啊、聖誔節的時間，來玩一玩
turing my home into an IoT demo room.
把家裡變成IoT的demo room
Pull out the pin,
可以把它的腳全部拿下來，小小一片
and connect with a electrical relay, put into the wall,
做個像繼電器之類的，埋在牆壁裡面
pretty good.
還滿不錯的
So first, I like the small form factor.
所以第一個，我們喜歡它的form factor
And second, I'm familiar with Linux,
第二個，我Linux還算滿熟的，雖然不敢說是最厲害
so the development work is not difficult.
所以我覺得開發對我來講，很方便
Besides programming with the familiar NodeJS,
那它除了用大家最耳熟能詳的NodeJS，去寫程式之外
of course it could be done with native C,
當然也可以用native C啊之類的，這不用講了
and Python could be used, too.
然後還可以用Python
Team Makee will introduce how to use Python with 7688,
待會Makee團隊跟大家介紹Python怎麼用
and Bo-Ju Chen is here,
再來NodeJS的大大陳伯儒在這邊
he'll introduce the NodeJS development environment.
跟大家介紹NodeJS開發環境
After the session, you could have a talk with Yihui,
今天結束之後，或許你們可以找Yihui交流一下
they just ported Lua to RePhone, a LinkIt ONE platform.
因為他前陣子在把Lua porting到RePhone，就是LinkIt ONE上面
Lua is another good choice,
Lua我覺得是另外一個選擇
my Wio Link was turned into a GoPro remote this afternoon,
像我的Wio Link，今天做的GoPro remote
just developed with Lua.
就是用Lua寫的
This is the program I wrote this afternoon.
最後，我想分享的，是今天下午在這邊寫的程式
It was developed with Lua.
這是用Lua寫的
Turning Wio Link into a WiFi GoPro remote.
然後把Wio Link變成GoPro的WiFi remote
push the button to take a photo.
按一下就會拍照
This part is connecting to the GoPro,
接到我的GoPro
and this is GPIO, interrupt triggering,
然後，這個是GPIO，中斷觸發
After triggered, calling the REST API of GoPro,
中斷觸發之後，對GoPro發出REST API request
There's a web server inside GoPro, it has lots of commands,
GoPro裡面有一個web server，所以它有很多command
Hackers hacked it and put documents on the Internet.
hacker把它hack出來，整理成文件，放在網路上
But I felt that it must be a intentionally leaked by GoPro company,
但是我覺得這明明是GoPro官方流出來，要給大家玩的
or, it could not have such details.
不然怎麼可能那麼清楚
I just gave a speech in another Makerspace yesterday,
我昨天剛好在另一個創客空間演講
also stated that GoPro is my favorite IoT product until now,
我也是講GoPro是目前為止我最喜歡的IoT產品
or say WoT product.
或者說WoT的產品
We could use boards like Wio Link, 7688,
我們就可以用像Wio Link、7688
make peripherals for it in just a few steps.
很快幫它打造一些周邊
Hereafter, there will be such a product,
以後就變成像這種產品
with a build-in server.
本身就是一台server
Google have an idea, called "physical web",
Google有個概念，叫physical web
just like this.
似乎就是想要這樣子做
We could work surround such a product,
那我們就環繞著一些產品
consider it as a server, and make peripherals for it
把它當server，幫它製作周邊
this is somewhat outside the topic of my presentation,
這已經有點跳脫今天我要講的主題
just share with you.
就只是大家分享一下
.
我的任務就是，講到大家都進來
Recently, in the MakerPro community,
最近大家應該在網路上，在MakerPro的社團裡面
Chang-You Guo organized a 7688 study road map,
看到郭長祐，幫大家整理了一份7688的study roadmap
I felt it's a good material.
我個人覺得滿好的
For example, in my projects, used only 7688, not Duo,
像在我的project裡面，其實只用到7688，沒有用到Duo
because I used Wio Link or ESP8266 to connect to sensors.
因為我是拿Wio Link或是ESP8266，去接感測器
the communication between them, is not via physical connection such as UART.
那兩者之間，就不是用什麼UART實體方式去連接
It used CoAP protocol.
是用CoAP的協定
so in my way of implementation,
所以如果以我的部署方式來講的話
I just need 7688.
其實我只需要7688
So 7688, 7688 Duo, or Arduino, their areas of application,
所以7688、7688 Duo、或者Arduino，到底可以用在什麼地方
and how to study with them,
或是怎麼樣去學習
Chang-You's article is very good.
我覺得長祐寫得很不錯
So I invited him to go here, have an introduction for everyone,
所以今天特別商請他過來，跟大家介紹一下
and what he has learned.
他的一些心得
If you have any idea,
如果各位有什麼其它的想法
.
或者是不同意見的話
we could discuss further
我們都可以互相討論
Welcome Chang-You,
那我們請長祐
My session ends here, thank you.
我的session就到這邊結束，謝謝大家